A Guide to the Alberta Pfeiffer Architectural Collection, 1929-1976
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Alberta Pfeiffer Architectural Collection, 1929-1976
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-017
10.3 cu. ft. 15 Boxes, 3 Folders
Graduated from the University of Illinois--Urbana/Champaign in 1923 as one of the first women to achieve a degree in architecture at that institution. The collection contains drawings, photographs, and correspondence of her architectural career. Most projects are residential, and the collection consists of approximately 250 different designs for various jobs.
Pfeiffer, Alberta Raffl
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Alberta Pfeiffer Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1988 and 1993.
Biographical Note
Architect of Hadlyme, Connecticut; born in Red Bud, Illinois (1899). Pfeiffer was one of the first women to study architecture at the University of Illinois--Urbana/Champaign where she graduated first in her class (1923). She was also the first woman to win the American Institute of Architects School Medal.
She began her 55 year career as an architect at the Chicago firm Tallmadge and Watson. After a year she returned to the University of Illinois for graduate work. In 1925, she moved to New York City where she worked with the Harrie T. Lindberg architectural firm until she set up practice in Hadlyme with her husband, Homer F. Pfeiffer, in the early 1930s.
Their practice was mainly residential focusing on design and renovations in the area surrounding Hadlyme, Connecticut. In 1940, Homer joined the Navy to supervise the construction of naval housing, hospitals, and other facilities while Alberta continued their firm's work on her own. After the war Alberta established her own private practice and flourished in the post-war boom recalling during the 1950s and 1960s she was never without a project and often had as many as ten designs on her desk at the same time. At her retirement in 1977 she had designed and/or renovated over 250 projects.
She was active in many professional and community groups joining the Society of Connecticut Craftsmen (1935) and a lifetime member of the Connecticut Society of Architects. Pfeiffer was a member of the local board of Education and the Zoning Board, and was involved in mental health issues and activities.
Pfeiffer died in 1994.
Scope and Contents Note
Collection contains 15 boxes and 3 oversize folders consisting of drawings, photographs, and correspondence relating to Pfeiffer's architectural career. Most projects are residential, and the collection contains approximately 250 different designs for various projects.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
There is an article about the acquisition of the Alberta Pfeiffer Architectural Collection in the Fall 1990 IAWA Center News, the International Archive of Women in Architecture newsletter.
Index Terms
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.
Local Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Contents List
- Professional Papers
  - Christmas Cards, n.d. (Box-folder 15|7-8)
  - Clippings, 1974, 1986 (Box-folder 15|9)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1939; 1977 1936-1939 (Box-folder 15|10-11)
  - Correspondence, IAWA, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 15|12)
  - Mental Health Legislation Correspondence, n.d. (Box-folder 15|13)
  - Military Plaque Design, 1966 (Box-folder 15|14)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 13/Drawer 5/Folder 3, Box-folder 15|15)
  - Seminaries for Clergy, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 15|16)
  - Watercolors, school work competitions, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 13/Drawer 5/Folder 1)
- Projects
  - Hobart Thompson Residence, Job 02, 1933 (Box-folder 1|1)
  - Earnest Ely Residence, Job 03, 1934 (Box-folder 1|2)
  - Henry 0'Neil Residence, Job 06, 1934 (Box-folder 1|3, Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Andrew J. Pizzini Residence, Job 07, 1934 (Box-folder 1|4)
  - O. Glenn Saxon Residence, Job 08, 1934 (Box-folder 1|5)
  - Ralph Bellany Residence, Job 09, 1934 (Box-folder 1|6)
  - Luke Finlay Residence, Job 14, 1935 (Box-folder 1|7)
  - Paul P. Swett Residence, Job 16, 1935 (Box-folder 1|8)
  - T.W. Goodrich Residence, Job 17, 1935 (Box-folder 1|9)
  - Henry Hull Residence, Job 18, 1936 (Box-folder 1|10)
  - Matthew Griswold Residence, Job 19, 1936 (Box-folder 2|1)
  - R. W. Huntington Residence, 1936 (Box-folder 2|2)
  - Adolph Levi Residence, Job 21, 1936 (Box-folder 2|3)
  - J.M. Mitchell Residence, Job 22, 1936 (Box-folder 2|4)
  - Elser Pool Residence, Job 25, 1936 (Box-folder 2|5)
  - Guy Pearce Jones Residence, Job 26 (Box-folder 2|6)
  - Robert Bradford Residence, Job 30, 1936 (Box-folder 2|7)
  - Alfred Sanford Residence, Job 31, 1937 (Box-folder 2|8)
  - Lyne Church, Job 32, 1937 (Box-folder 2|9)
  - Philip. S. Owen Residence, Job 33, 1937 (Box-folder 3|1)
  - Thomas Nason Residence, Job 34, 1938 (Box-folder 3|2)
  - Jones Kennel, Job 35, 1937 (Box-folder 3|3)
  - Holbrook Residence, Job 36, 1937 (Box-folder 3|4)
  - Kehoe Residence, Job 37, 1937 (Box-folder 3|5)
  - Lyne Church, Job 38, 1937 (Box-folder 3|5, Box-folder 3|6)
  - Moodus Savings Bank, Job 39, 1937 (Box-folder 3|7)
  - Peck Residence, Job 41 (Box-folder 3|8)
  - Chappel Residence, Job 43, 1938 (Box-folder 3|9)
  - Wilson Residence, Job 43, 1938 (Box-folder 4|1)
  - Pizzini Residence, Job 46, 1938 (Box-folder 4|2)
  - Norton Residence, Job 48, 1938 (Box-folder 4|3)
  - Tremaine Residence, Job 49, 1938 (Box-folder 4|4)
  - Reaser Residence, Job 50, 1938 (Box-folder 4|5)
  - Tremaine Servants Quarters, Job 52, 1939 (Box-folder 4|6)
  - Clifford Scott Residence, Job 53 (Box-folder 4|7)
  - Meloney Brown Residence, Job 55 (Box-folder 4|8, Box-folder 4|9)
  - Whitney Studio, Job 56, 1939 (Box-folder 5|1)
  - Holbrook Residence, Job 60, 1940 (Box-folder 5|2)
  - Ferguson Residence, Job 61, 1949 (Box-folder 5|3)
  - Inglis Griswold Residence, Job 63, 1940 (Box-folder 5|4)
  - Bar-T-Bar Land and Cattle Co., Job 64, 1940 (Box-folder 5|5)
  - Shaw Residence, Job 65, 1941 (Box-folder 5|6)
  - Sorenson Residence, Job 66, 1944 (Box-folder 5|7)
  - Wharton Residence, Job 67, 1941 (Box-folder 5|8)
  - Manley Residence, Job 68, 1941 (Box-folder 5|9)
  - Pizzini Residence, Job 69, 1941 (Box-folder 5|10)
  - Seidler Residence, Job 70, 1941 (Box-folder 5|11)
  - Kihn Residence, Job 71, 1942 (Box-folder 5|12)
  - Proudfoot Residence, Job 72, 1942 (Box-folder 5|13)
  - Kehoe Residence, Job 75, 1945 (Box-folder 5|14)
  - Manville Residence, Job 76, 1947 (Box-folder 5|15)
  - Ritchie Residence, Job 78, 1945 (Box-folder 6|1)
  - Buck Residence, Job 80, 1946 (Box-folder 6|2)
  - Kehoe Residence, Job 81, 1945 (Box-folder 6|3)
  - Various Church Plans, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 15|6)
  - Samuels Residence, Job 85, 1947 (Box-folder 6|4)
  - Chidsey Residence, Job 86, 1947 (Box-folder 6|5)
  - Brenmin Residence, Job 87, 1947 (Box-folder 6|6)
  - Brummer Residence, Job 88, 1947 (Box-folder 6|7)
  - Ely Residence, Job 90, 1947 (Box-folder 6|8)
  - Brown Residence, Job 91, 1947 (Box-folder 6|9)
  - Knollenberg Residence, Job 92, 1947 (Box-folder 6|10)
  - Church Residence, Job 95, 1947 (Box-folder 6|11)
  - Ondek Residence, Job 97, 1947 (Box-folder 6|12)
  - Peggy's Catalog, Job 98 1948 (Box-folder 6|13)
  - Kuvalanka Residence, Job 100, 1948 (Box-folder 6|14)
  - Edward Lyman Residence, Job 101, 1948 (Box-folder 6|15)
  - Tremaine Residence, Job 102, 1948 (Box-folder 6|16)
  - Steele Residence, Job 104, 1948 (Box-folder 7|1)
  - McKee Residence, Job 105, 1949 (Box-folder 7|2)
  - Adams Residence, 1949 (Box-folder 7|3)
  - Bradford Residence, Job 107, 1950 (Box-folder 7|4)
  - Lake Residence, Job 108, 1955 (Box-folder 7|5)
  - Hewett Residence, Job 112, 1950 (Box-folder 7|6)
  - Bent Residence, Job 113, 1950 (Box-folder 7|7)
  - Emerson Residence, Job 114, 1950 (Box-folder 8|1)
  - Griswold Residence, Job 115, 1950 (Box-folder 8|2)
  - Franchetti Residence, Job 116, 1950 (Box-folder 8|3)
  - Ely Residence, Job 117, 1950 (Box-folder 8|4)
  - Bennet Residence, Job 119, 1951 (Box-folder 8|5)
  - Fisher Residence, Job 121, 1951 (Box-folder 8|6)
  - McKee Residence, Job 122, 1951 (Box-folder 8|7)
  - Jonnke Residence, Job 123, 1951 (Box-folder 8|8)
  - Reynolds Residence, Job 124, 1951 (Box-folder 8|9)
  - Jewett Residence, Job 125, 1951 (Box-folder 8|10)
  - Griswold Residence, Job 126, 1951 (Box-folder 8|11)
  - Bernstein Residence, Job 127, 1952 (Box-folder 8|12)
  - Morrison Residence, Job 128, 1952 (Box-folder 8|13)
  - Hoedebeake Residence, Job 129, 1952 (Box-folder 8|14)
  - Humpal Residence, Job 131, 1953 (Box-folder 9|1)
  - Hosford Residence, Job 134, 1953 (Box-folder 9|2)
  - Selden Kitchen, Job 135, 1953 (Box-folder 9|3)
  - Morrison Porch, Job 136, 1953 (Box-folder 9|4)
  - Maud Sargent Residence, Job 137, 1953 (Box-folder 9|5)
  - Ely Farm Residence, Job 138, 1953 (Box-folder 9|6)
  - Termaine Barn, Job 139, 1953 (Box-folder 9|7)
  - Willows Residence, Job 140, 1953 (Box-folder 9|8)
  - Halperin Residence, Job 141, 1953 (Box-folder 9|9)
  - Spaulding Residence, Job 142, 1953 (Box-folder 9|10)
  - Morrison Residence, Job 143, 1953 (Box-folder 9|11)
  - Sisk Residence, Job 144, 1953 (Box-folder 9|12)
  - Holmes Residence, Job 145, 1954 (Box-folder 9|13)
  - Swan Residence, Job 146, 1954 (Box-folder 9|14)
  - Griswold Residence, Job 147, 1954 (Box-folder 9|15)
  - Bernstein Residence, Job 148, 1954 (Box-folder 10|1)
  - Jewett Residence, Job 149, 1954 (Box-folder 10|2)
  - Cone Residence, Job 150, 1954 (Box-folder 10|3)
  - Halperin Barn Residence, Job 150, 1955 (Box-folder 10|4)
  - Ryerson Residence, Job 151, 1954 (Box-folder 10|5)
  - Chandler Residence, Job 152, 1954 (Box-folder 10|6)
  - Telichet Residence, Job 153, 1954 (Box-folder 10|7)
  - Holbrook Residence, Job 154, 1954 (Box-folder 10|8)
  - Randall-Mills Residence, Job 155, 1954 (Box-folder 10|9)
  - Blenner-Hassett Residence, Job 156, 1955 (Box-folder 10|10)
  - De Saulniers Residence, Job 157, 1955 (Box-folder 10|11)
  - Richardson Residence, Job 158, 1955 (Box-folder 10|12)
  - White Residence, Job 159, 1955 (Box-folder 10|13)
  - Fire House, Job 160, 1955 (Box-folder 10|14)
  - Ryerson Residence, Job 162, 1958 (Box-folder 10|15)
  - Westerbeit Residence, Job 162A, 1956 (Box-folder 10|16)
  - Brevoort Residence, Job 162B, 1956 (Box-folder 10|17)
  - Edwards Residence, Job 162C, 1956 (Box-folder 10|18)
  - Fisher Residence, Job 162C, 1956 (Box-folder 10|19)
  - Aager Residence, Job 164, 1955 (Box-folder 11|1)
  - Garfinkel Residence, Job 165, 1956 (Box-folder 11|2, Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Brevillier Residence, Job 166, 1956 (Box-folder 11|3)
  - Kenney Residence, Job 167, 1956 (Box-folder 11|4)
  - Goodrich Kitchen, Job 168, 1956 (Box-folder 11|5)
  - Whitaker Residence, Job 169, 1956 (Box-folder 11|6)
  - Morrison Residence, Job 170, 1957 (Box-folder 11|7)
  - Turner, Jr, Job 171, 1957 (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Murtz Residence, Job 172, 1957 (Box-folder 11|8)
  - O’Conner Residence, Job 173, 1958 (Box-folder 11|9)
  - McDonnell Residence, Job 174, 1958 (Box-folder 11|10)
  - Hayes Residence, Job 175, 1958 (Box-folder 11|11)
  - Kearns Residence, Job 176, 1958 (Box-folder 11|12)
  - Sheffield Residence, Job 177, 1959 (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2, Box-folder 11|13)
  - Kengor Residence, Job 179, 1959 (Box-folder 11|14)
  - Copp Study, Job 180, 1959 (Box-folder 11|15)
  - John J. Speis Jr. Residence, Job 181, 1959 (Box-folder 11|16)
  - Buck Residence, Job 182, 1959 (Box-folder 11|17)
  - Delinks Residence, Job 183, 1959 (Box-folder 11|18)
  - Hamilton Jerret Residence, Job 184, 1959 (Box-folder 1|19)
  - Baldwin Residence, Job 185, 1959 (Box-folder 11|20)
  - Webster Residence, Job 186, 1959 (Box-folder 11|21)
  - Moriarty Residence, Job 187, 1959 (Box-folder 11|22)
  - Simpson Residence, Job 188, 1959 (Box-folder 11|23)
  - Ely Residence, Job 189, 1959 (Box-folder 12|1)
  - Kenyon Residence, Job 190, 1959 (Box-folder 12|2)
  - Speirs Residence, Job 191, 1959 (Box-folder 12|3)
  - Jerett Residence, Job 192, 1960 (Box-folder 12|4)
  - Howard Bawns Residence, Job 193, 1960 (Box-folder 12|5)
  - Harold Fair Residence, Job 194, 1960 (Box-folder 12|6)
  - Allyn Bown, Jr. Residence, Job 195, 1960 (Box-folder 12|7)
  - Henry Bowes Residence, Job 195, 1960 (Box-folder 12|8)
  - Davies Residence, Job 197, 1960 (Box-folder 12|9)
  - Luke Residence, Job 197A, 1960 (Box-folder 12|10)
  - Webster Bedroom Wing, Job 198, 1960 (Box-folder 12|11)
  - Girls Scouts, Job 199, 1960 (Box-folder 12|12)
  - Hal Baly-Madison Residence, Job 200, 1961 (Box-folder 12|13)
  - Rauch Residence, Job 201, 1961 (Box-folder 12|14)
  - Allen Residence, Job 202, 1961 (Box-folder 12|15)
  - Martinson Residence, Job 203, 1961 (Box-folder 12|16)
  - Fulton Residence, Job 204, 1961 (Box-folder 12|17)
  - Bennet Residence, Job 205, 1961 (Box-folder 12|18)
  - Hayleton Residence, Job 206, 1961 (Box-folder 12|19)
  - Hodlyn Residence, Job 208, 1962 (Box-folder 12|20)
  - Russel (in Hadlyme) Residence, Job 209, 1962 (Box-folder 13|1)
  - Shaw Residence, Job 210, 1962 (Box-folder 13|2)
  - Morrison Residence, Job 211, 1963 (Box-folder 13|3)
  - HoH, Job 212, 1963 (Box-folder 13|4)
  - Spencer Residence, Job 214, 1963 (Box-folder 13|5)
  - Irvine Residence, Job 214A, 1963 (Box-folder 13|6)
  - New Allen Residence, Job 215, 1964 (Box-folder 13|7)
  - Marer Residence, Job 216, 1964 (Box-folder 13|8)
  - Bloom Residence, Job 217, 1964 (Box-folder 13|9)
  - Harty Residence, Job 218, 1965 (Box-folder 13|10)
  - Sheffield Garage, Job 220, 1964 (Box-folder 13|11)
  - James F. Orr Residence, Job 221, 1964 (Box-folder 13|12)
  - Phillip Gordon Residence, Job 222, 1965 (Box-folder 13|13)
  - Renato Tiezzi Residence, Job 223, 1965 (Box-folder 14|1)
  - Han Rennhard Residence, Job 224, 1966 (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2, Box-folder 14|2)
  - Fisher Study, Job 225, 1967 (Box-folder 14|3)
  - Speirs Rental Cottage, Job 226, 1967 (Box-folder 14|4)
  - Brevillier Bay Window, Job 227, 1967 (Box-folder 14|5)
  - Smith Residence, Job 228, 1967 (Box-folder 14|6)
  - Hostnik Residence, Job 229, 1967 (Box-folder 14|7, Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Speirs Residence, Job 230, 1968 (Box-folder 14|8)
  - Stanley Peterson Residence, Job 231, 1968 (Box-folder 14|9)
  - North School House, Job 231A, 1968 (Box-folder 14|10)
  - Metcalfe Residence, Job 232, 1969 (Box-folder 14|11)
  - Haser Residence, Job 232, 1969 (Box-folder 14|12)
  - Griswold Residence, Job 234, 1970 (Box-folder 14|13)
  - McFarland Residence, Job 235, 1970 (Box-folder 14|14)
  - Sheffield Residence, Job 236, 1971 (Box-folder 14|15)
  - Plimpton Residence, Job 237, 1971 (Box-folder 14|16)
  - Hostnik Residence, Job 238, 1972 (Box-folder 14|17)
  - Cole Residence, Job 238, 1972 (Box-folder 14|18)
  - Murray Residence, Job 240, 1972 (Box-folder 14|19)
  - Hood Residence, Job 241, 1972 (Box-folder 14|20)
  - Van Halem Residence, Job 244, 1974 (Box-folder 14|21)
  - Brevillar Residence, Job 247, 1974 (Box-folder 14|22)
  - Littlefied Residence, Job 247, 1977 (Box-folder 14|23)
  - Roger Hilsman Residence, Job 249, 1973 (Box-folder 14|24)
  - Williams Residence, Job 249, 1975 (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2, Box-folder 12|25)
  - Friedman Residence, Job 250, 1976 (Box-folder 14|26)
  - Armour, Job Unknown, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Hilley Residence, Job Unknown, n.d. (Box-folder 15|3)
  - Kihn Residence, Job Unknown, 1938 (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Lyme Elementary School, Job unknown, 1949 (Box-folder 15|1)
  - Neilson Residence, Job Unknown, 1958 (Box-folder 15|2)
  - Ruby Boyer Miller, Job Unknown, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 13\Drawer 5\Folder 2)
  - Sargeant Residence, Job Unknown, n.d. (Box-folder 15|4)
  - Williams Residence, Job Unknown, n.d. (Box-folder 15|5)